[
{
    "question": "Describe how sound waves propagate through a medium.",
    "answer": "Sound waves are longitudinal waves that propagate by expanding or contracting. Expansions are known as rarefactions and contractions are called compressions. This wave is created by some sort of vibrating object that moves back and forth and compresses and expands zones of particles."
},
{
    "question": "When designing a fluid system where you want to maximize the exit fluid static pressure out of the system, what could you do to the tubes to ensure that they have small pressure drops? Assume that you can change the tubes and that the flow is laminar.",
    "answer": "To minimize the pressure drop through a pipe, there are a few things you could do. You can increase tube diameter or length which can reduce shear stress on your flow. Thus, it will decrease your pressure drop. What principle?"
},
{
    "question": "Why is it a reasonable assumption to say that sound waves are adiabatic? Also, just because they’re adiabatic does this mean that temperature is constant?"
    "answer": "Sound waves are adiabatic because they are so instantaneous that it can be assumed that heat can’t transfer which is the only condition for something to be adiabatic. However, just because heat can’t transfer doesn’t mean that the particle's temperature is constant. Sound waves undergo adiabatic compressions and rarefactions which can cause heating and cooling."
},
{
    "question": "Say you have a subsonic flow (M > 0.3) through a tube with friction of a small diameter . Why can’t you make this tube as long as you want? Assume your system is adiabatic and you want to keep the gas velocity constant. Ignore tube pressure losses from friction."
    "answer": "You can’t make these tubes as long as you want because the shear on the fluid will reduce its area and it will choke (M = 1). Fanno Flow happens when you have an adiabatic, compressible flow through a tube with friction."
},
{
    "question": "Why are normal shocks not isentropic?"
    "answer": "Normal shocks are characterized by sudden collisions between a supersonic flow and fluid particles.The shock creates a rapid compression zone that is inherently irreversible. For something to be considered isentropic, it must have no irreversibilities so normal shocks can’t be isentropic."
},
{
    "question": "Describe the types of expansion out of a supersonic nozzle and explain the conditions by which each expansion type forms."
    "answer": "When the ambient pressure is greater than the exit pressure of the flow, the flow is overexpanded and converges immediately after exiting the nozzle. When the ambient pressure is less than the exit pressure of the flow, the flow is underexpanded and forms diverges immediately after exiting the nozzle. When the ambient pressure equals the exit pressure, the flow is fully expanded."
},
{
    "question": "Is it possible to create a cryogenic pump that operates at 100% efficiency? Explain why or why not using thermodynamics principles."
    "answer": "Efficiency is the output work divided by the input heat. By the Kelvin Planck statement, it's impossible for a device to convert all of the heat into work. Losses always happen so a cryogenic pump could never operate at 100% efficiency."
},
{
    "question": "Describe what shaft work is."
    "answer": "Shaft work is the work contribution to a fluid from a rotating shaft that does work on the fluid through torque. Many fluids rely on shaft work for pressure through impellers or other types of turbomachinery."
},
{
    "question": "Name the 3 conservation laws that are fundamental in thermodynamics and fluids and briefly describe them."
    "answer": "The three conservation laws are energy, momentum, and continuity. Continuity says that mass flow rate is always constant in a system. Momentum relates the fluid's momentum and its force as well as inlet and exit pressures. Energy describes the relationship between heat into a system and work done by a system."
},
{
    "question": "The Merlin Engine by SpaceX is the most reliable rocket engine ever and is the engine for the Falcon 9 launch vehicle. Calculate the exit area of the nozzle given the following values: Expansion Ratio = 16, Cp = 6.0755 kJ/(kg * K), gamma = 1.13, mdot = 266 kg/s, T_0 = 2958 K, and P_0 = 9.7 MPa. You can assume that the flow is choked at the throat."
    "answer":{
        "code": "\n        import numpy as np\n\n        gamma = 1.4 # specific heat ratio\n        exp_rat = 16 # expansion ratio\n        Cp = 6.0755 # Cp at throat, [kJ/kg * K]\n        P_0 = 9.7 * 1000000 # inlet stagnation pressure [Pa]\n        mdot = 266 # mass flow rate [kg/s]\n        T_0 = 2958 # inlet stagnation temperature [K]\n\n        # Using a gas flow table, find non-dimensional mass flow rate at M = 1\n        ndmfr = 1.2810\n\n        # Solve for Throat Area\n        A_t = (mdot * np.sqrt(Cp * T_0))/(P_0 * ndmfr)\n\n        # Solve for Exit Area\n        A_e = A_t * exp_rat\n\n        print("Exit Area:", A_e, "m^2")\n        ""  "\n\n        } \n},\n{\n    "question": "You have an incompressible fluid flowing through a venturi. There are pressure transducers before the inlet and at the throat of the venturi which measure 800000 and 850000 Pa respectively. Calculate the throat velocity if the inlet velocity is 20 m/s. The fluid density is 786 kg/m^3."\n    "answer":{\n    "code": "
    import numpy as np

    rho = 786 # density [kg/m^3]
    v1 = 20 # velocity, [m/s]
    P1 = 800000 # pressure [Pa]
    P2 = 850000 # pressure [Pa]

    # Use bernoulli's eqn. to find v2
    v2 = np.sqrt(((P1 - P2) + 0.5 * rho * v1**2)*(2/rho))

    print("Throat Velocity", v2, "m/s")
        "\n\n        } \n},\n{\n    "question": "A pitot static probe measures ambient pressure as 101,325 Pa and static pressure inside the probe as 89,000 Pa. If air density is 1.25 kg/m^3, calculate the airplane velocity. Assume no wind.\n    "\n    "answer":{\n    "code": "
    import numpy as np

    P1 = 101325 # air pressure [Pa]
    P2 = 98000 # static pressure in probe [Pa]
    rho = 1.3 # density [kg/m^3]

    # Use Bernoulli's Eqn.
    v = np.sqrt((2 * (P1 - P2))/rho)

    print("Airplane Velocity", v, "m/s")
        "\n\n        } \n},\n{\n    "question": "You’re designing a tube for gas to flow through to pressurize a tank. The gas is moving at M = 0.45 and is therefore compressible. The tube diameter is 0.25” and has a friction factor equal to. Assume adiabatic. Calculate the tube length needed to choke your flow."\n    "answer":{\n    "code": "
    import numpy as np

    M = 0.45 # mach number
    D = 0.25 # diameter [m]
    Cf = 0.034 # friction factor

    # Lookup fanno flow coefficient in the gas flow table for M = 0.45
    ffc = 1.5664

    # Solve for Lmax
    Lmax = (ffc * D)/(4 * Cf)

    print("Tube Length:", Lmax, "m")
        "\n\n        } \n},\n{\n    "question": "You’re designing a system where you want to greatly increase temperature. You do this with a normal shock and you want to characterize your temperature rise after your shock. Plot this temperature as a function of mach number. T1 = 3100 K and gamma = 1.13."\n    "answer":{\n    "code": "
    import numpy as np
    import matplotlib.pyplot as plt

    T1 = 3100 # Temperature [K]
    gamma = 1.13 # specific heat ratio

    # create mach number vector
    M = np.linspace(1, 5, 100)

    # solve for temp post shock
    T2 = T1 * ((1 + ((gamma - 1)/2) * M**2) * (((2*gamma)/(gamma - 1)) * M**2 - 1))/(M**2 * (((gamma + 1)**2)/(2*(gamma - 1))))

    # plot
    plt.plot(M, T2)
    plt.xlabel("Mach Number")
    plt.ylabel("Temperature [K]")
    plt.title("Mach Number vs. Temperature [K]")
    plt.show()
        "\n\n        } \n},\n{\n    "question": "You’re designing a kerosene line that is 6 ft long and can be minimum 0.25”. It goes directly from your main fuel valve to your combustion chamber in a rocket engine so you want to minimize your pressure drop across this tube to less than 20 psid. Plot different tube sizes vs. pressure drop and find the smallest tube. You can assume your flow is laminar. Dynamic viscosity = 1.92E-3 kg/m*s, rho = 800 kg/m^3, and mdot = 7 kg/s."\n    "answer":{\n    "code": "
    import numpy as np
    import matplotlib.pyplot as plt

    mu = 1.92 * 10**-3 # dynamic viscosity [kg/m*s]
    rho = 800 # density [kg/m^3]
    mdot = 7 # mass flow rate [kg/s]
    length = 6 * 0.3048 # length [m]
    min_psid = 20 # pressure drop [psid]

    # create tube size vector
    t_d = np.linspace(0.25, 1.5, 100)

    # solve for velocity vec
    v = mdot/(rho * (((t_d * 0.0254)**2 * np.pi)/4))

    # Calculate pressure drop
    dp = ((8 * mu * v * length)/(((t_d * 0.0254)/2)**2)) * 0.000145038

    # plot
    plt.plot(t_d, dp)
    plt.plot(t_d, min_psid * np.ones(len(v)))
    plt.xlabel("Tube Diameter [in]")
    plt.ylabel("Pressure Drop [psi]")
    plt.title("Tube Diameter [in] vs. Pressure Drop [psi]")
    plt.show()
        "\n\n        } \n},\n{\n    "question": "The BE-3 turbopump uses 8.9 MW of heat and does 6.9 MW of work on its propellants. Calculate the efficiency of this turbopump.	"\n    "answer":{\n    "code": "
    import numpy as np
    import matplotlib.pyplot as plt

    Q = 8.9 # Heat [MW]
    W = 6.9 # Work [MW]

    # calc efficiency
    eff = W/Q

    print("Turbopump Efficiency:", eff*100, "%")
        """
        } 
},


]